בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody, today's דף daf is ל"ט lamed tet
39, כנגד k'neged the 39 מלאכות melachos I guess. We are picking
up on ל"ח עמוד ב' lamed chet amud bet and we're dealing
with this interesting debate. The משנה Mishnah discussed you've been entrusted fruit
and it's rotting. Are you supposed to sell it, which has not
been your charge from the owner, but do you sell it anyway
to protect the owner's investment? And there was a debate at what
stage would you sell it. And the גמרא Gemara sort of presents
a parallel, but the גמרא Gemara points out not the same debate
in terms of somebody's taken captive and their lands are laying fallow,
do you have a relative who will hopefully see this as their
property as well because they might eventually inherit it or they might
have inherited it already, and do you have them go ahead and
work the land in order to protect the person's investment and to
ensure the person will continue to get a benefit out of the
land? So that's the question about מורידין קרוב לנכסי שבוי. maridin karov
l'nichsei shavuy. So we pick up in the following place in the
גמרא, Gemara, ל"ח עמוד ב'. lamed chet amud bet. מיתיבי, Meisvei,
רבי
אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: From where can I already figure out
from the fact the verse says, this is by the
קללה, klala, or not the קללה, klala, but a general curse, וחרה
אפי והרגתי אתכם בחרב, v'charah api v'haragti eschem becharev, I will, my
anger will be kindled against you and
I will smite you with the sword, I'll kill you with the
sword. I already know that נשיכם אלמנות ובניכם יתומים, nisheichem almanos u'veneichem
yetomim, obviously
I
could figure out that your wives are going to be widows and
your sons will be orphans. That's what happens when the head of
the family is killed. So
why does the end of the verse have to spell that out?
מלמד Melamed to teach you שנשיכם מבקשות לינשא ואין מניחין אותן, shenisheichem
mevakshos lihnasei v'ein manichin osan,
it's going to be the worst. They're going to be אלמנות almanos
but not even אלמנות almanos that can get remarried. They'll want to
get remarried but the בית דין Beis Din won't let them because
the head of the household will be possibly killed in war but
you won't know. בניהם רוצים לירד לנכסי אביהם ואין מניחין אותן, Bneichem
rotzin lereid l'nichsei avihem v'ein manichin osan, and then the children would
like to take possession of the father's property because they believe the
father is dead and has been killed in war, and the בית
דין Beis Din won't allow them. Okay, so what is this? Anyway,
that's the דרשה. drasha. So it's really just like a type of
a non-halakhic, you know, דרשה drasha on the פסוק. pasuk. But the
גמרא Gemara is saying one minute, it sounds like somebody goes off
to war, you don't know if he's dead, and the kids can't
go ahead and, you know, and use the property and they can't
go ahead, so that seems like אין מורידין קרוב לנכסי שבוי, ein
maridin karov l'nichsei shavuy, that you can't allow a relative, the children
could be adult children, you cannot allow them to work the land
if you don't know what has happened to the father. So that's
the דרשה. drasha. So how does שמואל Shmuel deal with that, who
says מורידין? maridin?
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא: Amar Rava: לירד ולמכור תנן.
lereid v'limkor tnan. No, no, no,
it means they can't take full possession of the land. You know,
this דרשה drasha on the פסוק, pasuk, they can't go ahead and
sell off their father's estate. But that doesn't mean that they can't
work the fields one minute and benefit from it, you know, that
helps the father's investment and would help them as well. Okay, so
no, all that means is that they can't take full possession of
the property, so it's not a challenge to שמואל. Shmuel. So the
גמרא Gemara says הוה עובדא בנהרדעא, hava uvda b'nahardea, so there was
a case in נהרדעא Nahardea where somebody was taken captive, lost at
war, you don't know what happened, and the question was should the
children now start working the land? ופשטה רב ששת מהא מתניתין, u'pashata
Rav Sheshet mehah matnisin, and רב ששת Rav Sheshet sort of, you
know,
applied this ברייתא braita here, which was really from אבות דרבי נתן
Avot d'Rabbi Natan about בניכם יתומים, beneichem yetomim, that says no, from
here we see that אין מורידין קרוב לנכסי שבוי, ein maridin karov
l'nichsei shavuy, that the child is not allowed to go ahead and
start using, again, using is the wrong word, but like taking care
of the property and tilling the land, you know, when we don't
know what has happened to the father. Okay, so he ruled that
this was absolute, I'm sorry, you can't use. אמר ליה רב עמרם
לרב ששת, Amar lei Rav Amram le-Rav Sheshet, so רב עמרם Rav
Amram said to רב ששת: Rav Sheshet: דילמא לירד ולמכור תנן. dilma
lereid v'limkor tnan. He said what רבא Rava said, maybe all that
ברייתא braita means is that the kids cannot really fully possess it
and sell it off, but maybe we can have them go and
work the land? So maybe that's what it means. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, so he said back to him: דילמא מפומבדיתא את? dilma mipumbedisa
at? Maybe that's what it means, maybe you're one of those פומבדיתא?
Pumbedisa? דמעייל פילא בקופא דמחטא, d'mayil pila be-kufa d'machta, that try to
squeeze an elephant through the eye of a needle. Okay, so there's
that phrase, alright, comes up one other time in the גמרא. Gemara.
So you well maybe it means this, well maybe a lot of
things. Okay, maybe we could get an elephant through the eye of
a needle. And such a crazy suggestion, but let's see what his
response is: ודומיא דנשיהם. v'dumya d'nisheihem.
It's similar to the discussion about your wives are אלמנות, almonos, which
means a wives אלמנות almonos means that there’s nothing they can do.
So here too מה התם כלו, mah hasom klalo, the same way
there the wives can’t do anything in the sense of can’t be
married to anyone, you
know, have no can take no advantage, I know it’s a funny
word, but anyway, you know, about the do nothing based on the
possibility that the guy might be dead. So אף הכא נמי כלו,
af hacha nami klalo, here too also there’s nothing you can do,
you can’t go into the field at all. Of course you could
have said the opposite, you could have said for a woman to
be remarried is like that, you know, is more like is exactly
parallel to selling off that property. It’s sort of that sense of
like, you know,
the full assumption of the guy’s death. Whereas to work the land
is not the full assumption of his death, it’s dealing with the
uncertainty of his death. So anyway seems like a reasonable way to
read that ברייתא, baraita, but this was the pushback. Yes.
Is there a statute of limitations on this? For instance, let’s say
the guy would be 125 years old.
Ah, at what point do we assume that he might be dead
just in terms of the time? Right, yeah, that’s a good question.
You know, like like do we assume like can we declare him
dead after seven years? Like you can’t do that for a remarriage,
that’s the whole discussion in יבמות, Yevamos, whether you can do that
for this issue that we’re dealing with here about taking possession of
the property, you know, that’s a good question. I don’t know, it’s
a good question. All right, so let’s take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומרינן כנכסי שבוי תנאי היא.
umareinan ka nichsei shavui tana hi.
So we’ve said it’s a debate of Rav and Shmuel and question
if this piece of אבות דרבי נתן Avos de-Rabbi Noson proves one
way or the other, but we can actually say it’s a debate
of תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, דתניא, detanya, taught in the ברייתא, baraita, היורד
לנכסי שבוי, hayored lenichsei shavui, somebody who is goes down to work
the fields of a person who was taken captive, אין מוציאין אותו
מידו. ein motzi'in oso mi-yado. You do not take that out of
his hands, which means basically, so here’s the question which we haven’t
raised explicitly: this guy’s working the fields of the captive, what happens
to all of the, you know, all the way the field has
now produced, all the produce of the field, who gets to keep
it? So, you would think if the point of it is is
to ensure that the owner doesn’t lose out all the benefit that
the owner at least gets to keep the majority of it or
whatever, that’s what we’re going to see a little while an idea
that it’s אריס. aris. The guy who works it gets a portion
of it, we mentioned that yesterday, gets a portion of it, and
the owner gets the larger, you know, the two thirds of it.
Okay, this first statement in this ברייתא baraita seems to to say
that the person who works it gets to keep it all, which
then raises the question about how does that benefit the owner? But
it could benefit the owner because you know leaving a field fallow
is not good for I mean once every so many years you
do, but in general leaving it fallow isn’t good for the field
either. So let’s take a look what this ברייתא baraita says. היורד
לנכסי שבוי אין מוציאין אותו מידו. hayored lenichsei shavui ein motzi'in oso
mi-yado. You do not take the produce out of his hand. ולא
עוד אלא אפילו שמע שממשמשים ובאים, velo od ela afilu shama she-memashmeshin
ba'in, even if he heard that the original owners were like on
their way back, okay? He heard reports oh it turns out the
guy isn’t dead and actually you know there’s a report that he’s
coming in on the next ship.
ממשמשים memashmeshin I don’t know, it means like they’re on their way,
they’re like you know they’re stirring up, right, they’re stirring up and
coming, so I mean, וקדם ותלש ואכל, ve-kadam ve-talash ve-achal, he says
oh my god, I hear that somebody there’s a report that he’s
coming in in the next ship which is docking in two weeks,
time to harvest the grain, okay? And so he literally plucked it
out, like I guess he started picking all the apples off the
tree because he’s entitled to the produce but not what’s on the
land. Okay, so הרי זה זריז ונשכר, harei zeh zariz veniskar, this
guy has alacrity and is rewarded, you know, yes he’s totally entitled.
יישר כח. yashar koach. Which is so funny like when we’re doing
this to benefit presumably the owner protect the owner’s investment, so why
are we so giving this guy יישר כח? yashar koach? We’ll see
about that. How okay. ואלו הן נכסי שבויים, ve-elu hein nichsei shevuyin,
this is included in the category of somebody captive, we need a
standard category is somebody taken off captive and he might be dead.
Okay, but here’s some other here’s parallel categories. הרי שהיה אביו ואחיו
או אחד מן המורישין הלך
למדינת הים, harei she-haya aviv ve-achiv o achad min ha-morishin halach limdinat
hayam, the father a brother anybody who would be he would be
in line to inherit went off to a far away country. ושמעו
בהן שמת, ve-shamu bahen she-meis, and he heard that they died. Haya
so that would be a case of נכסי שבוי. nichsei shavui. You
believe the person to be dead. Okay now that is a little
bit helpful to explain why he gets to keep all of the
produce because it’s not you don’t know whether he’s alive or dead,
but he actually believes that he is dead. Okay and then when
you’re working it, you know what we’re actually going to say is
even though
to some degree what we should say is well until you can
prove he’s dead you can’t use it. We’re going to say you
know what we’re going to go by that enough to let to
let you take possession of it and you can actually treat it
as your own and you can actually fully
fully benefit from the produce. If it turns out he’s alive you’ll
give the land back to him and you’ll keep the produce. Okay
and that’s a seen as a win-win. You get to benefit from
it it’s not that it lays fallow and if you he no
well we’re now dealing with the case that maybe he was but
he’s believed to be dead and he’s off at war he’s believed
to be
dead that's. So that explains why you get to fully keep the
produce because א, aleph, you benefit from it, why should—why should it
lay there and just go—everybody go to waste? And if you you
believe it to be your own you'll take care of it as
an owner and hopefully you know it'll keep the land in good
condition if and when he does come back. Okay, so that's at
least the case when he's believed to be dead. In the case
when he's maybe is dead we'll deal with that later. But now
you understand why he gets full possession of the produce. Okay. Now,
היורד לנכסי נטושין מוציאין אותם מידו. hayored lenichsei netushin motzin otam miyado.
If somebody goes down to abandoned fields, not this case of שבויים
shevuyin like a guy taken captive who is reported dead, might be
dead, but an abandoned field, then you would take it out of
his hands.
ואלו הן נכסי נטושין, ve-elu hein nichsei netushin, the
following things are produce of an abandoned field: הרי שהיה אביו או
אחיו או אחד מן המורישין הלך לו למדינת הים, ha-rei she-haya aviv
o achiv o echad min ha-morishin halach lo limedinat hayam, they went
to the overseas, ולא שמעו להם שמתו, velo shamu lahem she-meitu, you
didn't hear that they died. You know, two years ago they went
to France, they haven't come back yet, I think I'm going to
start working his field. Okay, so that's a case where he's not
taken captive, he's not off to war, he's just some faraway country
and you haven't heard from him for a while. So there, why
what he there
there's no reason you well let's we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara.
ואמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל שמעתי שהנטושין כשבויים. ve-amar Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel shamati she-netushin kishvuyin. I heard that's the same thing. I heard
that if they're faraway, you have no idea, you know, there was
no communication, who knows what could have happened to him, he's been
away for too long, that's a reasonable thing like a שבוי, shavuy,
good reason to suspect he's dead that we should take care of
his property. Okay, and do a win-win. Now, היורד לנכסי רטושין, hayored
lenichsei retushin, if you go down to רטושין retushin is even worse
type than abandoned. רטושין retushin is I don't know, like I can't
think of of different degrees of abandoned.
My Jastrow translates to abandoned.
And what does it translate נטושין netushin as? Abandoned.
They're both abandoned. Okay, anyway the גמרא's Gemara going to say רטושין
retushin means almost like, like you know, I don't know, like negligently
abandoned, okay, discarded or whatever. Anyway, מוציאין אותם מידו. motzin otam miyado.
In that case you
you take it out of the guy's possession and there's no debate.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel doesn't say the guy
gets to keep on working it because this is something that the
owner there's no legitimate reason why you should be working the owner's
field even if the owner has completely ignored and abandoned it, you'll
see in a minute the owner is around so you have no
right to be doing it. ואלו הן נכסי רטושין, ve-elu hein nichsei
retushin, the following are called this worse abandoned field: הרי שהיה אביו
או אחיו או אחד מן המורישין כאן, ha-rei she-haya aviv o achiv
o echad min ha-morishin kan, they're they're here, they're living here, ואינו
יודע להיכן הלכו, ve-eino yodeia le-heichan halachu, meaning nobody now, it's not
that they're here סתם stam they're still in their home, it's like
does anybody know where Frank went? No, I don't know, he didn't
tell me, whatever, but okay, but it's not like you know they
went far away and they haven't returned, you just don't know where
they are. He didn't tell his business to you. Now of course
you could say guy didn't tell his business to anybody who knows
חס ושלום chas veshalom who knows what could have happened to him.
But anyway the גמרא Gemara says that in that case we're going
to assume that he is just being irresponsible, okay, and then he
hasn't given anybody permission to do his field, presumably he could have.
There's no evidence that like when he goes far away we say
something could have happened to him far away, but here we assume
you know he's a responsible adult so we don't have the right
to do this. One minute. So that's the three levels, okay? One
that's debated when they're in faraway, one that clearly everybody agrees when
reports that he's dead or taken captive, and one where we just
don't know what's happening which is like leave it alone. Now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי שנא הני דקרי להו נטושין ומאי
שנא הני דקרי להו רטושין? mai shena hanei de-karei lehu netushin u-mai
shena hanei de-karei lehu retushin? Why is the case where he's overseas
and where more worried that something happened called נטושין netushin and the
ones where he's just being irresponsible presumably being irresponsible we're calling רטושין?
retushin? So נטושין netushin top of לז עמוד א, lamed-zayin amud aleph,
נטושין דבעל כרחו, netushin de-ba'al korcho,
נטושין netushin means that something might have happened against his will. It's
more drastic, okay? דכתיב והשביעית
תשמטנה ונטשתה, dichshiv ve-hashvi'it tishmetenna u-netashtah, the שמיטה Shmita where you shall
let it lay fallow, you shall release it and God imposes it,
אפקעתא דמלכא, afkasta de-malka, that's God is forcing that on people. That's
something that's therefore it's sort of like it's an act of God.
Exactly. So therefore if the guy's overseas, we don't know what happened
to him, we're afraid that some unforeseen circumstance happened, his ship sank,
whatever, some act of God happened and therefore we go ahead and
we will start you know doing the field. רטושין דמדעתן, retushin de-mida'atan,
רטושין retushin means that people are, you know, are with you know
on their own decision, you know, choosing to leave it to abandon
it, דכתיב, dichshiv, that's at least how it appears to us,
אם על בנים רוטשה, eim al banim ruttasha, a mother on her
children are left abandoned and from the context of that פסוק pasuk
רש״י Rashi discusses it means sort of like willfully abandoned. So so
therefore
anyway fine, therefore anyway that's different degrees, okay? So if the guy
might be dead, you go ahead, you work the field and the
heir works the field and if the guy shows up alive the
heir keeps the produce whatever. If he is not returning from overseas,
there's a debate whether the guy gets to keep the produce. If
he is just we don't know what happened to him and it
seems like he's just being
irresponsible then. Okay, תנא *Tana*, we start in a
ברייתא *Braita*. וכולן שיימינן כעריס *V'kulan shamnin k'aris*. Everybody is treated like
an עריס *aris* who goes and works the field and gets a
portion so therefore will get a portion, like let's say a third
of the produce. אהיי *Ahei*, now which of these three cases are
we talking about? אילימא אשבויים *Ilema ashvuyin*, if it's the first category,
people that are taken captive and that we've even described there's reports
that the guy might be dead? So or is dead. השתא זריז
ונשכר הוי *Hashta zariz v'niscar havei*. You said that this guy who
quickly harvests the field and hears the guy's returning whatever, it sounds
like he gets to keep it all, right? It says אין מוציאין
מידו *Ein motzi'in miyado*. So then you're giving him it all. מה
דאשבח מיבעיא *Ma d'ashbach mibaya*? So if he gets to keep everything
he harvested of course he's entitled to the improvement of the
field. So why do you have to say like he's an עריס
*aris* which is only a portion of the improvement, right? Here he's
entitled to everything as what it sounds like, everything that he did.
So it can't be in that case, that can't be the case.
אלא ארטושין
*Ela artushin*, the third category, where it seems to be willfully abandoned.
והא מוציאין אותם מידו קתני *V'ha motzi'in otam miyado katani*. But that
clearly everybody agrees he has no right and you give it all
back to the owner. So what's the middle case where he doesn't
keep it all but he keeps a portion of it? So the
middle case is the middle case. אלא אנטושין *Ela antushin*, the middle
case. Now למאן *L'man*, according to which opinion? אילימא לרבנן *Ilema l'Rabbanan*,
the רבנן *Rabbanan*, הא מוציאין אותם מידו *Ha motzi'in otam miyado*. They
say if he's just overseas even if he hasn't returned, we view
that as just willful negligence and you have no right to work
the field at all, it's totally against any בית דין's beis din,
*Beis Din's* okay, and you would have to give it all up
and it all goes back to the owner. אלא ואי רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, *Ela v'ei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*,
now let's say it's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* who says no, no, no, that case also
you work the field and you get to keep it. האמר שמעתי
שנטושין כשבויים *Ha'amar shamati she'netushin k'shvuyin*. But he says I treat this
like שבויים *shvuyin*, שבויים *shvuyin* is the first category and שבויים *shvuyin*
we say you get to keep all of it. So where is
this middle category, okay? So it seems like there's three scenarios but
only two categories. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says כשבויים ולא שבויים
*K'shvuyin v'lo shvuyin*. No, they're like the שבויים *shvuyin* category but they're
not the same. Okay, for רבן שמעון Shimon, בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel* the middle case is a middle category. כשבויים דאין מוציאין
אותם מידו *K'shvuyin d'ein motzi'in otam miyado*. It's like the first category
where you believe the guy is dead where you keep it all,
okay, so I mean where it says where you don't give it
all back, that's true, you don't give it all back. ולא שבויים
*V'lo shvuyin*, but it's not literally like the it's not the first
category. דאילו התם זריז ונשכר *D'ilu hatam zariz v'niscar*. There he gets
a יישר כח *yasher koach* and he gets to keep it all.
ואילו הכא שיימנא ליה כעריס *V'ilu hacha shamnan lei k'aris*. But here
you make you treat him like a sharecropper and he only gets
a portion. Okay, and if you take a look at רש״י Rashi
*Rashi*, right? רש״י *Rashi* explains why. רש״י *Rashi* says התם זריז ונשכר
הוי
*Hatam zariz v'niscar havei* דיטול הכל *d'yitol hakol*. You see the little
א *aleph* in brackets? It's about 25 lines down in the near
lines of רש״י *Rashi*. There's a tiny little print א *aleph* in
the square brackets. It starts a line. And then he says דאילו
התם זריז ונשכר *D'ilu hatam zariz v'niscar* דכיון ששמעו בו שמת *d'keivan
she'shamu bo she'met* כי נחית אדעתא דכולא פירא נחית *ki nachis ada'ata
d'cula peira nachis*. He was going down, I mean we didn't know
had confirmed reports, but the assumption was, even though it wasn't yet
let's say legally ruled on, the assumption was that he was dead.
So therefore this guy was treating himself as if he was the
full owner. And we feel he's entitled, like again it's a win-win.
He'll see himself as the real owner by now, he'll treat the
property
responsibly. Turns up the guy is alive, at least his property will
have been taken care of even if this guy will get all
the benefit. אבל aval, הכא דלא שמעו שמת *Aval hacha d'lo shamu
she'met*, the guy who just didn't return from overseas, למה דעתא דכולא
נחית *lama da'ata d'cula nachis*? So when you go down, you're going
down knowing that we don't know what the story is. Maybe he's
just having a really good time in France or maybe God forbid
something happened. So you're going down as a sense of like I'm
working the field knowing that it might be mine and it might
not be, knowing that it's undetermined yet whether the owner is still
okay. So in that case לכתחילה *lechatchila* you're working it with an
assumption that you'll get some for your efforts, maybe all, but not
necessarily and therefore you get a portion. So no, the רבנן *Rabbanan*
only disagree which is whether we interpret the fact that the guy
didn't return from מדינת הים Medinat Hayam. *medinat hayam* as enough of
a good basis to think maybe he's dead, does that give you
enough license? That gets back to the case in our משנה mishnah,
*Mishna*. Okay, maybe by not working it the owner is going to
lose out, but it's somebody else's property. When do we tip in
favor of trying to protect the value and when do we tip
in favor of don't handle somebody's property if you don't have the
right to? That's exactly the issue in our משנה mishnah. *Mishna*. So
Michael's point is a good one, right, this case of the guy
not returning from מדינת הים *medinat hayam* is parallel it was רבן
שמעון Shimon בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* in our משנה mishnah?
*Mishna* too, right? Yes, excellent. It's exactly parallel to רבן שמעון Shimon
בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* in both cases is more willing
to say maybe you shouldn't touch it but I'd rather protect the
investment. And the רבנן *Rabbanan* are saying you know what... I'd rather
not touch somebody's property if we don't have a good basis to
do it.
Even if it's going to go to pot.
Yeah, I mean, again, that's the question. At a certain rate of
depreciation, the rabbis would agree. That's what gets back. Exactly. So it's
not the same. The גמרא Gemara said it's not the same as
the case of the פירות peros in the משנה, but it's parallel.
Okay, so does everybody understand that? That's a, right, it's an interesting
question. It's parallel to the case of the פירות peros in the
משנה. It's different because here it's more about profit than about clear
loss, although there is some loss to the value of the property
and here you're going to get something for your efforts, but the
question still is, when do we go ahead and do it to
protect the owner's investment and when do we say we don't know
it's somebody else's property, hands off. So that's how you debate the,
that's the debate of the case when he didn't return from מדינת
הים.
But to support the guy's wife and children, you're allowed to work
the property, right? Because he has an obligation to support.
Well, no, you're more allowed to support them and then he owes
you the money. But no, I think it's the same story as
this, ממונא שמני. mammona samni.
You're not allowed to work the land and then sell it and
give it to them?
I don't know. I'd have to look, but that's not, that's not,
that's not ringing a bell, but maybe you're right. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, now, ומאי שנא מהא
דתנן, u'mai shna me'had tnan, so how is this different than that
which we taught? So we have these three categories, right? Believed to
be dead or it's extremely probable he's taken captive in wars, so
maybe strong suspicion that he might be dead where apparently you get,
where you get it all. Then the case where he hasn't returned,
who knows, possible, but it's much more of a doubt where you
get a portion of it and that's a debate of רבן שמעון
Shimon בן גמליאל, do you work it and get a portion or
not work it. And the case where most likely he's just being
irresponsible, where it's like you leave it alone. Okay.
Even if you, even if you say like רבן שמעון Shimon בן
גמליאל, you work it and you get a portion, that's only like
a third. Yeah, so the other two-thirds of the, of the profits
are held for the owner.
Yeah, presumably it's sold and the money is put in escrow.
Right, exactly, until the guy comes back.
Exactly. ומאי שנא מהא דתנן, u'mai shna me'had tnan, now how is
this different from which we taught in the משנה? Here you go
Michael, at least it is a case of husband and wife, though
not exactly yours. המוציא הוצאות על נכסי אשתו, hamotzi ho-tza'ot al nichsei
ishto,
somebody who is spending money on his wife's property, right? He gets
married and his wife brings in property that she retains title to
but he gets the benefit from, the נכסי מלוג. nichsei milog. Okay,
that's her like, so, so he now is going to, she brought
in these, you know, a thousand acres and this guy is great,
he's going to develop it or he's going to plow it and
plant it and he spends a lot of money on his, on
it to grow the wheat in this land that his wife brought
in. המוציא הוצאות על נכסי אשתו, hamotzi ho-tza'ot al nichsei ishto, הוציא
הרבה ואכל קימעה, hotzi harbe ve-achal kima, let's say he spent ten
thousand dollars this year and it only, he only, he only,
you know,
the harvest was a thousand dollars. He lost. It was a net
loss. או קימעה ואכל הרבה, o kima ve-achal harbe, the opposite, he
spent a thousand and the, and the wheat was worth ten thousand.
It was a huge gain. מה שהוציא הוציא ומה שאכל אכל. mah
she-hotzi hotzi u-mah she-achal achal. What he spent he spent and what
he ate he ate. Means don't come to the wife, you know,
the wife can't come and say, hey, I want a portion in
the profits. That's what it means that the husband is אוכל פירות.
ochel peros. And the husband can't come to the wife and say,
hey, you know, I want you to reimburse me for my loss.
No. So that's the arrangement. You get to keep all the פירות,
peros, you don't get to ask anybody for you know, and you
get to expend all the expenses, what happens happens. Okay. So anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says, well, let's say that's the same. I'm
going to go ahead and I'm going to work somebody's field, this
guy the נכסי שבוי, nichsei shavui, I mean whatever, the relative, and
let's just say he keeps all the profit but he suffers all
the loss. Now the funny thing is we do say that. That's
essentially what we say when the guy is suspected to be dead,
right? We say you get to keep all the profits, you get
to keep it all and presumably he doesn't reimburse you for any
expenses. But the גמרא Gemara, seems to be talking about the middle
case. Why is the middle case not that? It's a funny question.
I mean the גמרא Gemara just really wanted to bring this in
because this case is really essentially that first case where the guy's
believed to be dead, that the person who works somebody else's property,
you know, there are scenarios where you keep all the profit but
you don't get reimbursed for your expenses.
That would be like an אבידה, aveida, right? In other words, an
אבידה, aveida, you have to re-, the owner has to reimburse for
the expenses for the food for feeding the animal, keeping the animal
alive and stuff like that, right? That's the model, is it not?
Yeah, but that there there's no profit, right? I mean so that
is true, but here where there's a profit it sort of it,
it's yeah, exactly. Okay, so the גמרא, gemara but the good point.
אבל, so the גמרא gemara says, okay, הלא דמיא אלא להא, halo
damya ela le-ha, fine. The case of שבוי, shavui, presumably the case
of the אריס aris case of שבוי, shavui, the middle case where
you get a portion and so on, is similar to not to
the case of the wife but to the following case.
Okay. תנן, tnan, we have the, it's תנן, tnan, but it seems
like it is דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב חסדא. de-amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav Chisda. He never answered the question. Well, we're going to
explain why they're different cases. First we're going to put another case
on the table. המוציא הוצאות על נכסי אשתו קטנה, hamotzi ho-tza'ot al
nichsei ishto ketana, let's say it's his wife who's a minor. And
not his wife who's a minor because he married her because he
gave, you know, he married her through the father, but his wife
who's a minor that the father is dead and he married her
through the mother and
the brothers. In which case
it's only rabbinically married. And at any time this young girl could
say, you know what, I don't like you, you know... and walk
away. Okay, so she actually can sever the marriage while she is
still a קטנה. ktana. That's קידושי מיאון. kiddushei miun. So, in this
case, why is this similar to the middle case where you're not
sure if the guy is alive or dead?
You don't know whether or not she's going to actually be fully...
you don't know whether you're going to get to keep the land.
Exactly. And actually now this piece is two perfect models: in the
case where the husband is working the wife's property, his fully legal
wife's property, he is expected, you know, or reasonably expecting that property
to stay in his estate. Under what circumstances will the property that
his wife brought in remain his?
If she dies.
If she dies before him. Is it possible he'll divorce her? Well,
that'll be his own choice. That he'll die before, that's possible. But
anyway, by the way, in the ancient world, the wife was going
to die before the husband because of childbirth and all that. Anyway,
so he is expecting that property to stay in his estate. That's
like the guy who thinks his father is dead, doesn't know for
sure, and is working the property and he keeps and therefore you
keep it all. You suffer, you deal with the expenses, and you
keep it all. But the case of not knowing if the guy
is dead and getting a portion is the husband working his wife's
property and his wife is a minor and his wife at any
time could walk away. So he's not sure that that property is
going to remain his. According to, well, yeah. So, כמות שהוצאה זו
נכסי אשה כקטנה כמות שהוצאה נכסי אחר דמי. kemot shehotza zo nichsei
isha kektana kemot shehotza nichsei acher dami. It's like just going ahead
and deciding you're going to plow somebody else's field, you know, you're
going to start working somebody else's field
who isn't around. אלמא, alma, you see, כיון דלא סמכא דעתיה, keivan
dela samcha dateih, since he's not fully confident that it's going to
remain his, תקינו ליה רבנן, takinu lei rabanan, the rabbis established that
at least he would get a portion of it, right? You have
to be invested in order that you're going to take care of
it. Okay, so you will get a portion. כי היכי דלא לפסדינהו,
ki heichi dela laphsdinu, so he shouldn't waste it, he shouldn't basically
strip mine it. All right? Right? So, now the funny thing is
that I... אמר רבנן, amar rabanan, no that's רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
though. Well, no, it just means the rabbis in the generic. הכא
נמי, hacha nami, here too, תקינו רבנן כי היכי דלא לפסדינהו. takinu
rabanan ki heichi dela laphsdinu. Here also, the rabbis established that he
was an אריס, aris, that so therefore he should not go ahead
and basically just destroy it. Now, what I don't really get is
that what are we contrasting the אריס aris possibility to? Presumably, we're
contrasting the אריס aris possibility to getting nothing. But if you're getting
nothing, then what do you mean you're going to destroy it? You're
not going to destroy it; you're not going to do it at
all. Right? So if there's a concern that you're going to destroy
it, what, so what are we contrasting it to rather than what?
That you should get all of it? But if you get all...
what difference does it make if you think you're going to get
all, or you think you're going to get a portion? Either way,
you're not going to want to destroy it. Maybe if you think
you're going to get all of it, you're going to get a
bigger payoff right away. And therefore, you know, hey, like maybe my
minor wife will walk away, maybe my relative will turn back, and
that could be any time. So I'd better like, you know, get
as much profit from this as quickly as possible. Right. But you
could also say that even if you're only getting a third. But
maybe the point is that since the payoff is less, you're going
to... right, there's less temptation and if you want to really, you
know, fully get a lot of money, you know you have to
pace yourself. So that seems to be the point. Okay? You have
a suspicion whether the guy's going to return. We didn't want to
give you all; we're going to give you a portion, so therefore
you'll take better care of it, which is an interesting psychology. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. וכולן שמין להן כאריס.
vechulan shamin lahen ke'aris. So, and all of them, you treat like
an אריס. aris. So what does it mean all of them? So
far we only have this one middle category of not knowing if
the guy's dead. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכולן לאתויי מאי, vechulan
le'atuyei mai, what is that coming to include? לאתויי הא דרב נחמן
אמר שמואל:
le'atuyei ha de'Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel: שבוי שנשבה מורידין קרוב לנכסיו, יצא לדעת אין מורידין קרוב
לנכסיו.
shavui shenishba moridin karov lenichsav,
yatza lada'at ein moridin karov lenichsav. Did I skip a line? לאתויי
מאי לאתויי הא דרב נחמן אמר שמואל.
le'atuyei mai le'atuyei ha
de'Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. Not... okay, right, okay, so fine. To include
what רב נחמן אמר שמואל Rav Nachman amar Shmuel says, because here's
the teaching: שבוי שנשבה מורידין קרוב לנכסיו, shavui shenishba moridin karov lenichsav,
יצא לדעת אין מורידין קרוב לנכסיו. yatza lada'at ein moridin karov lenichsav.
If he's taken captive, you have the guy work the field. If
he, if he just went on his own on some trip and
the field's been abandoned for two years, you leave it alone. רב
נחמן Rav Nachman דידיה dideih אמר, amar, now רב נחמן Rav Nachman
himself in his own name says: בורח הרי הוא כשבוי. boreach harei
hu keshavui. Okay, if somebody actually runs away, okay, it's not like
he is taken captive, it's not like some people came and seized
him, but it's not like he's going on some trip. Okay? He's
running away from fear of the government. So that's like a שבוי.
shavui. That's a guy... because if he's in fear of the government,
now why? You should say if he's running away, it's not like
he might be dead. But the point is is that one of
the reasons we cannot work the field when the guy isn't here,
it's because we say people are adults, they're responsible for their own
property. If he's gone and he wanted that field worked, he should
have left some instructions, you know, maybe even if he hasn't returned
in a while, that gets back to the fact that he's far
away, but maybe he could have sent instructions. But if a guy
is in hiding from the government and is running away cause the,
you know, the police are coming to seize him, so then we
say he didn't have a chance, he's not able to leave instructions
and to send instructions. So in that case, even if he's not
dead, we don't say, hey, it's his own responsibility. And in that
case, actually we would, at least according to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
take care of his field for him. Okay. Now, what is the
case of בורח? boreach? Okay, בורח מחמת מאי? boreach machmat mai? Now,
what circumstances is the guy running away? אילימא מחמת כרגא, elima machmat
karga, היינו דאס? hainu das? So, okay, the government is after him
for back taxes, the IRS is coming after him, but he's not
like afraid for his life. So in that situation, he's had enough
time to, you know, to give instructions. And if he's not giving
instructions, he's responsible, okay, that we're not going to deal with his
property in that situation. Yeah, but everybody always pays their taxes. It's
not about that. It's about you don't feel that you're running for
your life. Okay, now I got it. אלא בורח מחמת מרדין. ela
boreach machmat mardin. No, running away because of murder. We have that
word again מרדין, mardin, murder. You remember מרדין מרדין mardin mardin from
בבא קמא? Bava Kama? Murder, murder. Okay, anyway, so, so he is
being, maybe he committed it, maybe he's suspected of it, but the
point is they're going after him and they're going to capture him,
they're going to kill him. So in that case, he's running away
and he's keeping quiet and he's not sending word, and therefore רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says we have רחמנות rachmanut on him, we're going
to take care of his property. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל:
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: שבוי שנשבה והניח קמה לקצור ענבים לבצור
תמרים לגדור, shevoy shenishba vehiniach kama liktzor anavim livtzor temarim ligdor, a
guy was taken captive. We've been dealing with the actual effort of
planting it. Let's say the stuff was immediately ready to be harvested,
right? He left all this stuff, right? The grain ready to be
harvested, the grapes to be harvested, the dates to be picked, זיתים
למסוק, zeitim limsok, the olives to be pressed. בית דין, beis din
in that case, בית דין יורדין לנכסיו ומעמידין אפוטרופוס וקוצר ובוצר וגודר
ומוסק. beis din yordin lenichasav uma'amidin apotropus vekotzer uvotzer vegoder umosek. In
that case, nobody deserves to profit from that. That takes minimal effort
and high profit, and בית דין just oversees that. They hire some
guy to be the overseer, the אפוטרופוס, apotropus, maybe they pay the
workers, okay? If the guy comes back, you know, they'll whatever they'll
get reimbursed for the expenses, but nobody is getting a big portion
of that. That we just, you know, take that, sell it, put
the money away for the owner. ואחר כך מורידין קרוב לנכסיו. ve'achar
kach moridin karov lenichasav. Afterwards, then when it requires real effort now
to keep on tending to the land, that's when you have the
relative, קרוב, karov, and he's going to get a portion of the
profits. So the גמרא Gemara says, ונוקמי אפוטרופא לעולם? venukmi apotropa l'olam?
So just have this אפוטרופוס, apotropus, just have this overseer, let him
handle it the whole time and never take a profit? And that'll
be of maximum benefit, you know, and he'll be an appointee of
the court and he'll be responsible for his position. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, אפוטרופא לדיקנני לא מוקמינן. apotropa lediknani la mukminan. We
don't appoint an אפוטרופוס apotropus for people with beards, meaning the דקנני,
diknani, זקנים, zekeinim, which basically means the standard אפוטרופוס apotropus is for
orphans and kids who can't handle their own affairs. Okay, not for
adults. Now the point is, okay, but this guy's an adult, but
he might be captured in war. But the way רש"י Rashi says
it is, an
אפוטרופוס apotropus does his work, it's like thankless work, you know, he
doesn't get paid, he doesn't get a profit, he does it for
the honor of being appointed by the court, okay, and that is
something that he'll be willing to do if you've got these poor
underage orphans that need somebody to take care of them. Alright, somebody
like this, okay, I feel bad he was taken
captive, but to standardly
do it for free?
Like you know?
Why not just hire him and he'll get a third or he'll
get a fourth then?
Well, if we're going to give the אפוטרופוס apotropus money, we might
as well give the קרוב karov money. Yeah, but he might not
be as I don't know. Anyway, the point is the אפוטרופוס apotropus
idea that you're doing it because of the honor of the court
and you're doing it for free and it's sort of thankless but
righteous service, that's something that we can do for this immediate short
term thing that people are willing to do for these underage orphans.
You're not going to get people to volunteer to do it for
this scenario. In that case, you get the relative and he gets
a portion of the benefits. That idea of that thankless work, you
know, is the joke, right? The guy, he's like the they tell
it either about the גבאי gabbai or the president, but I'll tell
it about the גבאי, gabbai, you know? His father comes to visit
him in the little village and he says, you know, and his
son is the גבאי gabbai of the שול, shul, and he says,
and he's looking for his son, it's the first time he's visiting
the village. So he goes to somebody and he says, you know,
do you know where my son חיים Chaim the גבאי gabbai is?
He says, חיים Chaim the גבאי? gabbai? That liar? That good-for-nothing? You
know, and goes block stam to make a laugh and then goes
to the next guy and says, you know, do you know where
my son? That ממזר? mamzer? That this? Whatever goes on and on.
So then he comes to him and says, חיים Chaim tell me,
he says, you know, you're the גבאי. gabbai. you do this work
for the שול, shul, it doesn't pay anything, it's a lot of
effort, you gotta deal with a lot of cranky people. Says, what
do you do it for? He says, Dad, I'll tell you. It's
for the כבוד. kavod. Anyway. All right. So. Not like rabbis ever
have to deal with that. All right. What we got? אמר רב
הונא. Amar Rav Huna. So says Rav Huna. All right. אין מורידין
קטן לנכסי שבוי. Ein moridin katan l'nichsei shavuy. You do not have
now that we've established this idea of having an an heir go
and do the work, the heir is an adult heir. It's not
a minor. You don't trust a minor to work the property. Okay?
So you don't if you have a minor even if he's an
heir go to the property of the guy taken captive. ולא קרוב
לנכסי קטן V'lo karov l'nichsei katan or the reverse. You don't have
a relative even an heir go and work the property of a
minor which is bizarre. The minor is taken captive, the minor might
be dead, right? Why not have somebody tend to the property? So
and so we'll see. ולא קרוב מחמת קרוב לנכסי קטן V'lo karov
machmat karov l'nichsei katan and not a one-degree removed relative or we'll
see what that is. Okay so now we're going to unpack this.
אין מורידין קטן לנכסי שבוי. Ein moridin katan l'nichsei shavuy. You don't
have a minor work the property of a שבוי. shavuy. דילמא מפסיד
להו Dilma mafsid lehu because he's a minor, he won't be responsible.
ולא קרוב מחמת קרוב לנכסי קטן V'lo karov machmat karov l'nichsei katan
so first we're going to leapfrog over the middle case, describe what's
a קרוב מחמת קרוב. karov machmat karov. באחי מאמא. Ba'achi mei'ima. Okay,
so the remember, the person who's working the property is somebody in
the line of inheritance. Okay? So the קרוב מחמת קרוב karov machmat
karov is that here's ראובן, Reuven, okay, here's his father יעקב Yaakov
and his mother right and his mother רחל, Rachel, okay, so there's
ראובן. Reuven. His קרוב karov is thank you. I wasn't doing the
biblical one but thank you. His brother is שמעון, Shimon okay. His
now קרוב מחמת קרוב karov machmat karov is actually we actually it
won't work. Somebody's got to stop leaving these things uncovered. Anyway. But
the קרוב מחמת קרוב karov machmat karov is let's say then, okay,
this is not the biblical example, okay. Let's say יעקב Yaakov dies
and לאה Leah here marries עשו, Esav, don't tell anybody, okay, and
לאה Leah has some other son, we'll call him Chris. Now okay
so so ראובן Reuven is taken captive. All right? ראובן Reuven is
taken captive. שמעון Shimon is the קרוב karov who would work and
he's a קטן, katan, okay? So ראובן Reuven is the קטן. katan.
So you would not have שמעון Shimon work the נכסי קטן, nichsei
katan, the נכסי קרוב nichsei karov who's a קטן. katan. We'll see
why, we don't know yet why. And you wouldn't have the קרוב
מחמת קרוב, karov machmat karov, שמעון's Shimon relative who's not ראובן's Reuven
relative, okay, you wouldn't wait. How they're just the same... wait, wait,
no, no, מאחי מאמא. mei'achi mei'ima. Yeah, well he he is ראובן's
Reuven relative in the same mother but not in terms of inheritance.
Inheritance goes through the father, okay. So this is a relative as
a relative, different father and you also don't have even you know,
don't have him inherit either. They might have property that שמעון Shimon
does brother if they're both brothers. I don't I don't know. I
can't figure that out right now. Okay, anyway, let's keep on going,
okay? And also Chris could be yeah, you do the Christian thing.
Because עשו Esav wanted to marry and also עשו, Esav, Christianity comes
from I know. All right, all right. All right. Shh. Got it.
Okay. All right. Moving on. Okay. So. All right, let's take a
look. So we have to figure out the middle case though which
is why שמעון Shimon can't work the property of ראובן Reuven who's
a קטן. katan. Why can't he protect that investment? So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ולא קרוב לנכסי
קטן. V'lo karov l'nichsei katan. Why? כיון דלא מחי אתי לאחזוקי ביה.
Keivan d'lo machi ati l'achzukei beih.
Here's the problem. The problem is the following. שמעון Shimon is going
to be working ראובן's Reuven field, okay, and he's going to be
working it for three years, five years even, but let's say three
years. Then ראובן Reuven comes back. He's okay. שמעון Shimon, is going
to say, oh, okay, but you know what? This was my field
all along. Because our father died, how did they have property? They
had different property,
right? יעקב Yaakov had died, ראובן Reuven had these fields, שמעון Shimon
had these fields. But now that for some reason ראובן Reuven has
been taken captive, שמעון Shimon is also working this field. Now ראובן
Reuven comes back and ראובן Reuven says, oh, thank you so much
for working my field. Give it back to me now. You can
keep the produce. And שמעון Shimon says, what do you mean your
field? This was part of my field of the inheritance. And I've
been working for it for three years and nobody has said anything
to me, okay, and you know, we're going to learn in בבא
בתרא Bava Basra if nobody sort of contests something in three years,
okay, so therefore we're afraid that he's going to make a claim
and as a potential heir of יעקב Yaakov that claim will be
believed. Okay. But he's a קטן katan and you
know, he's like he fears to stand up to his older brother.
Because if they were both גדולים gedolim wouldn't said that, right?
So the reason it's an issue about a קטן katan is
one minute...
Why are we doing all of that if we're talking about שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* and ראובן Reuven *Reuven*?
What, one more time?
Why do we do all the thing with the half-brother?
We're going to get to the half-brother in a minute. Let's first
figure out the שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* case though. One minute. Hold on,
let me just check רש"י Rashi *Rashi*.
I understand, I understand. One minute, one minute.
Yeah. So the point is, now for some reason, and I don't
fully understand this, okay, because the whole point is that—oh, okay, wait
a minute. Now actually I do understand this. Because I actually, okay,
the case is not that I misstated the case. The case is
not that ראובן Reuven *Reuven* was taken captive. Okay, if somebody is
taken captive, the idea that you're not complaining that somebody is working
your field is obviously irrelevant. The reason you're not complaining is because
you were taken captive in war. So take a step back, I
misexplained it. The point is ראובן Reuven *Reuven* is just a kid.
So maybe let's have his older brother, here's the question: should we
look at the case of a minor, the very—the normal case of
a minor like the case of somebody who is captive? You're a
five-year-old, nobody is taking care of your property, it's going to lay
fallow until you become an adult. Let's say your brother take care
of it for you. Okay, should we do that? So that's the
question. Okay. So a minor doesn't take care of his property of
his brother who is captive because you can't trust a minor to
take care of it. That's אין מורידין קטן katan, לנכסי שבוי shavui.
*Ein moridin katan l'nichsei shavuy*. Okay, but you also, in the normal
case of a minor, you don't say, "Hey, let's let the older
brother take care of the property because the minor can't take care
of his own property." You don't do that. Why not? Because if
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is taking care of ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s property—so again,
no captive here—שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is just in charge of ראובן *Reuven*'s
property because ראובן *Reuven*'s the kid, then ראובן *Reuven* will become an
adult a few years later and he'll say, "Give me back my
property," and שמעון Shimon *Shimon* will say, "What are you talking about?
It was always mine." Now if ראובן *Reuven* was an adult, ראובן
*Reuven* could prevent against that because ראובן *Reuven* could always protest and
say, "I want everybody to know שמעון *Shimon*'s working my property, but
it's really mine." Or have the opportunity to protest or whatever. But
if ראובן *Reuven*'s a kid, we're giving שמעון *Shimon* too much opportunity
to claim and exploit it and to claim it was always his
property. Now the question about the קרוב karev מחמת קרוב *Karov machamat
karov* is, oh, okay, but I got a solution. Let's let Chris
do it. Because Chris will never be able to claim that it
was his property because Chris isn't in any line to inherit from,
right? These, you know, to inherit from, from ראובן *Reuven*.
So he can't say, "Yeah, יעקב Yaakov? *Yaakov* died, he left this
to me." Right? Since he's in no line to inherit, nobody's going
to believe him that it's his property and they're going to say
ראובן *Reuven* was a kid, that's why he didn't say anything and
you're not believed that that's your property. So why can't we let
Chris do it? Okay. And maybe the thinking that we would is,
like Michael says, well, we'll get an אפוטרופוס apitropus *apotropus*, we'll find
somebody to take care of ראובן *Reuven*'s property. But don't let that
somebody be שמעון *Shimon* and don't even let it be a one-degree
removed relative because you're giving them too much opportunity to exploit. So
why are we giving Chris opportunity to exploit? Let's take a look.
Okay. So
אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava*,
so
the—maybe the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't explain. Somebody does. Hold on. שמע
מינה *shma mina*, אין מורידין קטן katan
לנכסי שבוי
*ein
moridin
katan
l'nichsei
shavuy*, ונכסי קטן katan. לאפוטרופוס *v'nichsei katan l'apotropus*.
So
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't say, so let me
just reread רש"י Rashi *Rashi*'s explanation. ונכסי קטן katan. לאפוטרופוס בנכסי הבאים
מחמת אחים אמיהן שנפלו להם מאבי אמם *V'nichsei katan l'apotropus b'nichsei ha-ba'im
machamat achim imeihen she-naflu la-hem m'avi imem*.
Oh,
okay, because here's what you're going to say, because what if you
let Chris do it, okay, here's the story, guys, here's why you
don't let Chris do it. Because if you let Chris do it,
Chris is going to say, "Sure, this isn't my property, but you
know whose property I've been working all along while I've been working
this? שמעון
*Shimon*'s." Okay? So because, you know, because—and since, yes, שמעון *Shimon* got
this from יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*, the same way שמעון *Shimon* would have
claimed, "I got this from יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* and I've been working
my property," if you let Chris do it, he'll make that claim
on behalf of שמעון *Shimon*. Okay? And that will be believed the
same way שמעון *Shimon*'s would be believed and then they'll split it
between them. They'll have some deal going, okay? So bottom line is
you've got the קטן katan *katan* who is—somebody needs to tend his
property. He's like the שבוי *shavuy*. Get somebody else. Don't get a
relative and don't even get a one-degree removed relative because they'll have
some scheme going and they'll claim that they were the heirs to
that property. All right, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this:
"Can't anyone claim, right?
Well, no normal person could claim that you're the heir to my
property. Like everybody knew that all these properties at one time belonged
to יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*. Okay? And then יעקב *Yaakov* died." If שמעון
works this, he's going to claim it's his.
But I'm just saying, it's like פלוני Ploni over there who comes
in and decides he's going to do a side deal
with שמעון also because he... Oh, yes, anybody could do it and
say I'm working it for שמעון, that's true, but I guess we're
more fearful that it's going to if it's a relative. Okay, אמר
רבא, Rava שמע מינה מדרב הונא, Shma mina mid'Rav Huna, we can
hear from רב הונא, Rav Huna, אין מחזיקין בנכסי קטן, Ein machzikin
benichsei katan, ואפילו הגדיל, Ve'afilu higdil, that
no normal person, right, the only concern is that somebody will claim
hey, this was my property I got from my father and that'll
be believed on its own terms. But a stranger who works, let's
say we got some total stranger here to work ראובן's field, right,
why aren't we afraid that that stranger will say yeah, that's my
property because I bought it from יעקב? So you see that if
somebody has is מחזיק machzik in the field of a קטן, katan
somebody is working the field of a קטן katan for many years,
he's not believed to say it's my field I bought it from
the father. Okay, because then nobody could work the field of the
קטן. katan So you're afraid that somebody will say it's mine, שמעון
will say it's mine I inherited it from my father, but you're
not afraid that a stranger will say yeah, I've been working this
field and I bought it from יעקב and ראובן never inherited it.
Because חזקה chazaka does not work when it's done to the field
of a קטן. ואפילו הגדיל, Ve'afilu higdil, even if the קטן became
an adult and he continued working it, okay, nevertheless it is since
he initially started working it when the guy was a קטן and
did not know his father's dealings, then there is no then the
fact that this stranger has been working this field gives no evidence
to the idea that that might really be that stranger's field because
the קטן was not in a position to protest. And then even
after the קטן became an adult, you assume this guy's been working
the field for the last five years, he did not know enough
to protest. All right. לא אמרן אלא באחי דאבא אבל באחי דאמא
לית לן בה. Lo amran ela b'achi d'abba aval b'achi d'ima leit
lan bah. And now this issue that we're concerned about relatives or
relatives of relatives is only a brother on the father's side. But
a brother on the mother's side where there's never a question that
he's not in a position to inherit, okay, that person could work
the field for his brother. That's Chris? No. Chris is related to
a brother on the father's side, so he might have a deal
going with a brother on the father's side. But a brother who
started on the mother's side, okay, יוסף, Yosef, right, who started as
a brother, I'm sorry, not יוסף, Yosef, it would have to be
some other, yeah, a brother anyway whatever, somebody who is a brother
only on the mother's side is לאה.
Leah. Does that, is Chris not on the mother's side? I'm so
sorry.
It starts with שמעון is a brother on the father's side, and
therefore if שמעון were to work it he'd be believed to say
that he inherited it. So Chris who's שמעון's brother can make a
similar claim on behalf of שמעון. But it starts, the initial link
to ראובן is a father side brother. If you had an initial
link that was only a mother side brother, that person would be
is never in the line of inheritance.
I think this is what you're saying.
If Chris, no, let's say שמעון did exist, but let's say that,
yeah, if שמעון didn't exist, thank you. Exactly. Thank you. If שמעון
did not exist you could have Chris, exactly, you could have Chris
work it, right. Okay. All right. So, okay, וארעא, V'ara'a, and even
this whole issue about working the field is only by land where
we're afraid that he's going to make a statement that this is
the land I inherited. אבל בבתי לית לן בה, Aval b'vatei leit
lan bah, but actually to in for houses it's not a problem.
Why? Because רש"י says if let's say I'm going in and our
father left us a lot of houses and I'm going to go
into the house and I'm going to take up residence in my
minor brother's house, you know because I'll tend it, I'll mow the
lawn, I'll see to it, I'll take care of it. So that's
not a problem that I'm going to claim it's mine. Why is
that not a problem? So רש"י says because houses there are like
neighbors around so they'll be able to challenge my
claim.
Fields
are out, out in the country, right, in the field. ובארעא נמי
לא אמרן אלא דלא עביד איטדא, U'v'ara'a nami lo amran ela d'lo
avid itda, and even by the land this issue about not working
your brother's land if he's a minor is only that there was
not some type of a document that laid out how the lands
were divided.
אבל עביד איטדא, Aval avid itda, if there was this type of
document that declared how the lands were divided, קלא אית ליה, kala
it lei, then everybody knows it and nobody's going to believe you
to say that this was always your land. לא היא, Lo hi,
and the גמרא says but you know what those distinctions are not
true. לא שנא אחי דאבא ולא שנא אחי דאמא, Lo shena achi
d'abba velo shena achi d'ima, I don't care if it's a father's
brother or mother's brother. לא שנא ארעא ולא שנא בבתי, Lo shena
ara'a velo shena b'vatei, I don't care if it's land, I don't
care if it's houses. לא שנא עביד איטדא ולא שנא דלא עביד
איטדא, Lo shena avid itda velo shena d'lo avid itda, and I
don't care about whether there is this document or not. לא מחתינן,
Lo machtinan, it is too dangerous to have a brother working the
property of his minor brother because he is too likely to claim
that it is his. Okay, now רש"י still wants to know how
he's going to claim it's his if it's just the case of
Chris and רש״י sort of explains what the scenario is. What is
he going to say?
Oh what Chris is going to say is that this field here
that we knew was יעקב’ס, Yaakov’s, it was never יעקב’ס. Yaakov’s. You
know why people were assuming this field was יעקב’ס? Yaakov’s? Because it
was my mom’s field that יעקב had been working as נכסי מלוג.
Nichsei Milog. So when יעקב died, ראובן never inherited it. My mother
inherited it, took it back, and now it’s mine. Okay so you
see if you can figure that one out anyway. Right, right, but
that it's a false claim. Okay anyway that’s the thing. You got
a minor, somebody’s gotta tend to his field, don’t be a relative.
Okay? Don't mix family and business. All right, moving on. All right,
but if it’s a stranger working the field, then he’s not believed
to say I bought it from the father because since he’s working
the field of a minor, his working the field of a minor
gives no presumption that it’s his because, you know, the minor didn’t
know the business. Okay. Now the גמרא says like this. ההיא סבתא,
Hahi safta, there was an old woman or a grandmother דהוו לה
תלתא בנתא, d'havu lah tlata banta, she had three daughters.
אישתבאי היא וחדא ברתא, ishtavai hi v'chada barta, she was taken captive
and one of her daughters. אידך תרתי בנתא, idach tarti banta, the
other two daughters שכיב חדא מנייהו, shchiv chada minaihu, one of them
died ושבקה ינוקא v'shavka yinuka and she left over
a child. So you have לאה Leah here who had three daughters,
okay, what are we going to call their names? I don't know.
Okay, we'll have שרה Sarah here. Okay, so she had three daughters,
רבקה, Rivka, רחל, Rachel, and לאה. Leah. Okay, now, okay, רבקה Rivka
was taken captive.
She's captive.
רחל Rachel died and left over little baby בנימין. Binyamin. שרה’ס Sarah's
captive also.
What? שרה’ס Sarah's captive also.
Oh yeah, שרה’ס Sarah's also captive, thank you. Okay. All right, they
were all taken by
אבימלך. Avimelech.
Okay, so they were taken captive, רחל Rachel died and left over
baby בנימין Binyamin and you’ve got לאה. Leah. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, now,
who’s going to work the fields of שרה? Sarah? Okay. היכי נעביד?
Heichi naavid? נוקמינהו לנכסי בידא דאחתא. Nokminhu l'nichsei b'yada d'achata.
Let's let לאה, Leah, the only adult in the picture who’s around,
work the fields of her mother.
דילמא שכיב סבתא, Dilma shchiv safta, maybe שרה Sarah is dead,
ואין מורידין קרוב לנכסי קטן. v'ein moridin karev l'nichsei katan.
Then לאה Leah can't work the fields because if שרה Sarah is
dead, it’s part of the fields are owned by בנימין. Binyamin. And
we can't have somebody work the fields of a minor, a קרוב
work the fields of a minor. נוקמינהו לנכסי בידא דינוקא. Nokminhu l'nichsei
b'yada d'yinuka.
Let's just let בנימין Binyamin here, you know, be the one who
works the field, at least work his own field. Right? Let's let
לאה Leah take her portion, she’ll take a third let’s say. Let's
let him at least work a third, we don't know what's happened
to רבקה. Rivka. Okay, she's dead. Let's let him work his portion,
okay. דילמא לא שכיב סבתא, Dilma lo shchiv safta,
oh no, because you only heard that שרה Sarah was dead. Well
maybe שרה Sarah isn't dead and if she’s not dead,
a minor is working the fields of an adult. Okay. So דילמא
לא שכיב סבתא ואין מורידין קטן לנכסי שבוי. dilma lo shchiv safta
v'ein moridin katan l'nichsei shavui.
Okay.
So you can't not have בנימין Binyamin work it and have לאה
Leah work it because maybe she's working the field of a minor.
You can't have בנימין Binyamin work a portion of it because maybe
a minor is working the field of a שבוי. So what are
you going to do? אמר אביי הלכך, Amar Abaye hilkach, here's how
you’re going to solve it. פלגא יהבינן לה לאחתא. Palga yahavinan lah
l'achata.
You give לאה Leah half. Why do you give לאה Leah half?
Because if שרה Sarah is alive, okay, then לאה’ס Leah's entitled to
work the whole field on behalf of שרה, Sarah, right, on behalf
of her mother. If שרה Sarah is dead, okay, then לאה Leah
is entitled to work her, you know, keep her portion and also
work the portion on behalf of רבקה, Rivka, right? Everybody with me?
Okay, so she is going to get half. ואידך פלגא מוקמינן
לה אפוטרופא לינוקא. V'idach palga mokminan lah apitropa l'yinuka. And
the other half you get an אפוטרופוס apotropus to work on behalf
of בנימין. Binyamin. Now the question is wait
a minute but what about רבקה’ס Rivka’s portion?
Hold on.
No,
so
the question is that
maybe. Maybe so we're going to suspect, we're going to assume for
now the possibility that both of them died. If both of them
died, okay, you can't have לאה Leia work the whole property, right?
Because then she would also be working the property of
בנימין. Binyamin. You guys with me? If both of them died, then
בנימין Binyamin is a partial heir, she can't work the whole property.
Okay, בנימין, Binyamin, why don't you split it? Have her work half
and בנימין Binyamin work half? Because if שרה Sara is alive, בנימין,
Binyamin, a minor, a ינוקא, yanuka, is working the property of a
שבויה. shevuya. So in the case that both of them died, what
you're going to do is you're going to give her half because
regardless she gets half. If everybody's alive, she's working their property. If
everybody's dead, she gets her half, so it's divided with בנימין. Binyamin.
And for בנימין's Binyamin half, he can't work it because maybe he's
working their property, so you have an אפוטרופוס apotropus take care of
בנימין's Binyamin half and therefore he'll be either preserving it for בנימין
Binyamin if שרה Sara is dead or preserving it for שרה Sara
if שרה Sara is alive. Okay? Okay, let's just read one more
case to finish this up. So the גמרא says like this: יהבינן
לה פלגא ומוקמינן אפוטרופוס לינוקא. yehavinan leh palga u-mokminan apotropus le-yanuka. רבא
אמר Rava amar no. מיגו דמוקמינן אפוטרופוס לפלגא מוקמינן ליה אפוטרופוס לאידך
פלגא. migu de-mokminan apotropus le-palga mokminan leh apotropus le-idach palga.
Since you have to get an אפוטרופוס apotropus anyway, right? We're just
going to get an אפוטרופוס apotropus to handle all the property, even
לאה's Leia share. Once you are hiring an אפוטרופוס apotropus. and he's
managing some of the property, he'll manage the whole property. That's רבא's
Rava position. Now, לסוף, lesof,
so that was when they thought both of them were dead. לסוף
שמעו דשכיבא סבתא. lesof shamu de-shachiva savta. Then they heard that שרה
Sara actually had died. My mistake was I was jumping ahead. שרה
Sara actually had died. Okay. לסוף, lesof, that's the problem that I
know what's coming. Okay.
Let's just finish this case. Where were we? שמעו דשכיבא סבתא. shamu
de-shachiva savta. אמר אביי תילתא יהבינן ללאה אחתה. Amar Abaye tilsa yehavinan
le-Leia achasa.
So we don't know what רבקה's Rifka story is. So אביי Abaye
says, okay, we don't know what רבקה's Rifka story is, but we
know that לאה Leia minimally has a third. Even if everybody is
alive, לאה Leia has a third, right? ותילתא יהבינן לינוקא. ve-tilsa yehavinan
le-yanuka.
And we know that minimally בנימין Binyamin has a third, because even
if רבקה's Rifka alive, he gets a third. Yep. Now the question
is, is רבקה Rifka alive? What do you do with רבקה's Rifka
third? All right, so ואידך תילתא יהבינן דנקא לאחתה. ve-idach tilsa yehavinan
danka le-achasa.
The other third you divide in half. Okay, you have two cases
of a sixth. A דנקא danka is a sixth. Okay. דנקא שיתא.
danka shisa. So if you've got here, so לאה Leia gets to
work a third plus a sixth to the half, right?
Yeah. Okay, anyway, so לאה Leia works this because ממה נפשך. mima
nafshach. If רבקה Rifka is dead, then לאה Leia gets this sixth,
that's her full half the property. If רבקה Rifka is alive, then
she's an adult working the property of a שבויה. shevuya. So this
sixth goes to לאה. Leia. This sixth again you don't know what
to do with it. If רבקה's Rifka dead, בנימין's Binyamin entitled to
it. But if רבקה's Rifka alive, then בנימין Binyamin can't work it,
he's a minor and he can't work the property of an adult.
ואידך דנקא מוקמינן אפוטרופוס לינוקא. ve-idach danka mokminan apotropus le-yanuka.
So similarly for this sixth we appoint an אפוטרופוס. apotropus רבא אמר
מיגו דמוקמי אפוטרופוס לדנקא, Rava amar migu de-mokmi apotropus le-danka,
once we're appointing an אפוטרופוס apotropus for any part of the property,
even just a sixth, מוקמינן אפוטרופוס לאידך דנקא. mokminan apotropus le-idach danka.
Oh no, so here he says we don't do for all because
in this case this is definitely their property. There's no question that
they're entitled to that, right? The only question about this is whether
רבקה's Rifka alive. This is the property that we don't know what
the story is. So רבא Rava says once we have an אפוטרופוס
apotropus on this sixth, we're going to have an אפוטרופוס apotropus, on
that. What?
Why did he do that? That second part, that's like obvious based
on the previous thing.
It's, I don't know, I think the point that רבא's Rava saying
that it's not an אפוטרופוס, apotropus when רבא expands it, it's not
an אפוטרופוס for all of the property because this property you know
that they inherited. It's just for the property in doubt. It is
pretty obvious. Okay, I don't know, for me it's helpful to spell
the whole thing out. Okay, okay, so that we will end with
that. Okay, so
whew, we got through that. We got through קטן בנכסי שבוי ושבוי
בנכסי קטן katan be-nichsei shevuy ve-shevuy be-nichsei katan and this very colorful
example, and to be continued over.